<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="pre5378Trust200902" docName="draft-abarth-cookie-01pre">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="HTTP State Management Mechanism">
      HTTP State Management Mechanism
    </title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Barth" fullname="Adam Barth">
      <organization abbrev="U.C. Berkeley">
        University of California, Berkeley
      </organization>
      <address>
        <email>abarth@eecs.berkeley.edu</email>
        <uri>http://www.adambarth.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2009"/>
    <workgroup>http-state Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the HTTP Cookie and Set-Cookie headers.</t>

      <t>NOTE:
      <list>
        <t>This document is currently a "straw-man" cookie proposal.  Much of
        the text herein is completely wrong.  If you have suggestions for
        improving the draft, please send email to http-state@ietf.org.
        Suggestions with test cases are especially appriciated.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines the HTTP Cookie and Set-Cookie header.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The terms user agent, client, server, proxy, and origin server have
      the same meaning as in the HTTP/1.0 specification.</t>

      <t>Fully-qualified host name (FQHN) means either the fully-qualified
      domain name (FQDN) of a host (i.e., a completely specified domain name
      ending in a top-level domain such as .com or .uk), or the numeric
      Internet Protocol (IP) address of a host.  The fully qualified domain
      name is preferred; use of numeric IP addresses is strongly discouraged.
      [TODO: What does "strongly discouraged" mean?]</t>

      <t>The terms request-host and request-URI refer to the values the client
      would send to the server as, respectively, the host (but not port) and
      abs_path portions of the absoluteURI (http_URL) of the HTTP request line.
      Note that request-host must be a FQHN.  Hosts names can be specified
      either as an IP address or a FQHN string.  Sometimes we compare one host
      name with another.  Host A's name domain-matches host B's if
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>both host names are IP addresses and their host name strings match
        exactly; or</t>

        <t>both host names are FQDN strings and their host name strings match
        exactly; or</t>

        <t>A is a FQDN string and has the form NB, where N is a non-empty name
        string, B has the form .B, and B is a FQDN string.  (So, x.y.com
        domain-matches .y.com but not y.com.)</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note that domain-match is not a commutative operation: a.b.c.com
      domain-matches .c.com, but not the reverse.</t>

      <t>Because it was used in Netscape's original implementation of state
      management, we will use the term cookie to refer to the state information
      that passes between an origin server and user agent, and that gets stored
      by the user agent.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="State and Sessions">
      <t>This document describes a way to create stateful sessions with HTTP
      requests and responses.  HTTP servers respond to each client request
      without relating that request to previous or subsequent requests; the
      technique allows clients and servers that wish to exchange state
      information to place HTTP requests and responses within a larger context,
      which we term a "session".  This context might be used to create, for
      example, a "shopping cart", in which user selections can be aggregated
      before purchase, or a magazine browsing system, in which a user's
      previous reading affects which offerings are presented.</t>

      <t>There are, of course, many different potential contexts and thus many
      different potential types of session.  The designers' paradigm for
      sessions created by the exchange of cookies has these key attributes:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>Each session has a beginning and an end.</t>

        <t>Each session is relatively short-lived.</t>

        <t>Either the user agent or the origin server may terminate a
        session.</t>

        <t>The session is implicit in the exchange of state information.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Outline">
      <t>We outline here a way for an origin server to send state information to
      the user agent, and for the user agent to return the state information to
      the origin server.</t>

      <section title="Syntax: General">
        <t>The two state management headers, Set-Cookie and Cookie, have common
        syntactic properties involving attribute-value pairs.  The following
        grammar uses the notation, and tokens DIGIT (decimal digits) and token
        (informally, a sequence of non-special, non-white space characters) from
        the HTTP/1.1 specification [RFC 2068] to describe their syntax.</t>

        <t>[TODO: Test this grammar.  I think there are many, many issue with
        this grammer.  For example, this grammar seems to permit whitespace
        around the "=", but I don't think that actually works.]</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
   av-pairs        =       av-pair *(";" av-pair)
   av-pair         =       attr ["=" value]        ; optional value
   attr            =       token
   value           =       word
   word            =       token | quoted-string
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Attributes (names) (attr) are case-insensitive.  White space is
        permitted between tokens.  Note that while the above syntax description
        shows value as optional, most attrs require them.</t>

        <t>NOTE: The syntax above allows whitespace between the attribute and
        the = sign.  [TODO: This is probably wrong, however.]</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Origin Server Role">
        <section title="General">
          <t>The origin server initiates a session, if it so desires.  (Note
          that "session" here does not refer to a persistent network
          connection but to a logical session created from HTTP requests and
          responses.  The presence or absence of a persistent connection
          should have no effect on the use of cookie-derived sessions).  To
          initiate a session, the origin server returns an extra response
          header to the client, Set-Cookie.  (The details follow later.)</t>

          <t>A user agent returns a Cookie request header (see below) to the
          origin server if it chooses to continue a session.  The origin server
          may ignore it or use it to determine the current state of the
          session.  It may send the client a Set-Cookie response header
          with the same or different information, or it may send no Set-Cookie
          header at all.  The origin server effectively ends a session by
          sending the client a Set-Cookie header with Max-Age=0.  [TODO: Need
          to say something about Expires here.]</t>

          <t>Servers may return a Set-Cookie response headers with any
          response.  User agents should send Cookie request headers, subject to
          other rules detailed below, with every request.</t>

          <t>An origin server may include multiple Set-Cookie headers in a
          response.  Note that an intervening gateway MUST NOT fold multiple
          Set-Cookie headers into a single header.  [TODO: Investigate how UAs
          cope with folded headers.]</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Set-Cookie Syntax">
          <t>Let an LWS character be either a U+20 (SPACE) or a U+09 (TAB)
          character.</t>

          <t>A user agent MUST use the following algorithm to parse the
          Set-Cookie header:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>[TODO: Deal with ',' characters.]</t>

            <t>If the header contains a ';' character:
            <list>
              <t>the name-value string is characters up to, but not
              including, the first ';', and the unparsed-cookie-attributes
              are the remainder of the header (including the ';' in
              question).</t>
            </list>
            Otherwise:
            <list>
              <t>the name-value string is all the character contained in the
              header, and the unparsed-cookis-attribues is the empty
              string.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>If the first non-LWS character of the name-value string is
            '=', remove it.</t>

            <t>If the name-value string contains a '=' character:
            <list>
              <t>the name string is the characters up to, but not including, the first '='
              character, and the value string is the characters after the
              first '=' character .</t>
            </list>
            Otherwise:
            <list>
              <t>the name string is empty, and the value string is the entire
              name-value string.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Remove any leading or trailing space from the name
            string.</t>

            <t>Remove any leading or trailing space from the value
            string.</t>

            <t>The cookie-name is the name string.</t>

            <t>The cookie-value is the value string.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>The user agent MUST use the following algorithm to parse the
          unparsed-attributes:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>[TODO: Figure out how to parse cookie attributes.]
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>After parsing the Set-Cookie heaer, the user agent *has
          recieved a cookie* from the origin server with name cookie-name,
          value cookie-value, and attributes cookie-attributes.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Set-Cookie Syntax">
          <t>The syntax for the Set-Cookie response header is</t>

          <t>[TODO: Valdiate this syntax.]</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>
   set-cookie      =       "Set-Cookie:" cookies
   cookies         =       1#cookie
   cookie          =       NAME "=" VALUE *(";" cookie-av)
   NAME            =       attr
   VALUE           =       value
   cookie-av       =       "Comment" "=" value
                           [TODO: Daniel Stenberg has never seen a cookie with
                           a comment.]
                   |       "Domain" "=" value
                   |       "Max-Age" "=" value
                           [TODO: Expires is clearly missing.]
                   |       "Path" "=" value
                   |       "Secure"
                           [TODO: HTTPOnly is also missing.]
                   |       "Version" "=" 1*DIGIT
                           [TODO: Version is likely a fantasy.]
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Here's the parsing rule for NAME:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Ignore any leading WS.</t>
            <t>Consume bytes until you reach "=" or ";".</t>
            <t>Let NAME be the consumed bytes with any trailing WS removed.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Informally, the Set-Cookie response header comprises the token
          Set-Cookie:, followed by a comma-separated list of one or more
          cookies.  Each cookie begins with a NAME=VALUE pair, followed by zero
          or more semi-colon-separated attribute-value pairs.  The specific
          attributes and the semantics of their values follows.  The NAME=VALUE
          attribute-value pair must come first in each cookie.  The others, if
          present, can occur in any order.  If an attribute appears more than
          once in a cookie, the behavior is undefined.  [TODO: Test what happens
          when attributes are multiply defined.]
          <list>
            <t>NAME=VALUE
            <list>
              <t>Required.  The name of the state information
              ("cookie") is NAME, and its value is VALUE.  NAMEs that
              begin with $ are reserved for other uses and must not be used by
              applications.  [TODO: I suspect the $ rule is a fantasy.]  The
              VALUE is opaque to the user agent and may be
              anything the origin server chooses to send, possibly in a
              server-selected printable ASCII encoding.   "Opaque"
              implies that the content is of interest and relevance only to the
              origin server.  The content may, in fact, be readable by anyone
              that examines the Set-Cookie header.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Comment=comment
            <list>
              <t>Optional.  Because cookies can contain private information
              about a user, the Cookie attribute allows an origin server to
              document its intended use of a cookie.  The user can inspect the
              information to decide whether to initiate or continue a session
              with this cookie.  [TODO: Does this actually exist?]</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Domain=domain
            <list>
              <t>Optional.  The Domain attribute specifies the domain for which
              the cookie is valid.  An explicitly specified domain must always
              start with a dot.  [TODO: Test what happens without a dot.]</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Max-Age=delta-seconds
            <list>
              <t>Optional.  The Max-Age attribute defines the lifetime of the
              cookie, in seconds.  The delta-seconds value is a decimal
              non-negative integer.  [TODO: Test negative integers.]  After
              delta-seconds seconds elapse, the client should discard the
              cookie.  A value of zero means the cookie should be discarded
              immediately.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Path=path
            <list>
              <t>Optional.  The Path attribute specifies the subset of URLs to
              which this cookie applies.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Secure
            <list>
              <t>Optional.  The Secure attribute (with no value) directs the
              user agent to use only (unspecified) secure means to contact the
              origin server whenever it sends back this cookie.  [TODO: We
              should give better implementation advice than this.]</t>

              <t>The user agent (possibly under the user's control) may
              determine what level of security it considers appropriate for
              "secure" cookies.  The Secure attribute should be
              considered security advice from the server to the user agent,
              indicating that it is in the session's interest to protect
              the confidentiality of the cookie's value.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Version=version
            <list>
              <t>Required [TODO: Unlikely].  The Version attribute, a decimal
              integer, identifies to which version of the state management
              specification the cookie conforms.  For this specification,
              Version=1 applies.  [TODO: Remove this attribute.]</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Controlling Caching">
          <t>[TODO: Should we go into this much detail here?  This seems
          redudant with the HTTP specs.]</t>

          <t>An origin server must be cognizant of the effect of possible
          caching of both the returned resource and the Set-Cookie header.
          Caching "public" documents is desirable.  For example, if the origin
          server wants to use a public document such as a "front door" page as
          a sentinel to indicate the beginning of a session for which a
          Set-Cookie response header must be generated, the page should be
          stored in caches "pre-expired" so that the origin server will see
          further requests.  "Private documents", for example those that
          contain information strictly private to a session, should not be
          cached in shared caches.</t>

          <t>If the cookie is intended for use by a single user, the Set-Cookie
          header should not be cached.  A Set-Cookie header that is intended to
          be shared by multiple users may be cached.</t>

          <t>The origin server should send the following additional HTTP/1.1
          response headers, depending on circumstances:  [TODO: Is this good
          advice?]
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>To suppress caching of the Set-Cookie header: Cache-control: no-
            cache="set-cookie".</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>and one of the following:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>To suppress caching of a private document in shared caches:
            Cache-Control: private.</t>

            <t>To allow caching of a document and require that it be validated
            before returning it to the client: Cache-Control:
            must-revalidate.</t>

            <t>To allow caching of a document, but to require that proxy caches
            (not user agent caches) validate it before returning it to the
            client: Cache-Control: proxy-revalidate.</t>

            <t>To allow caching of a document and request that it be validated
            before returning it to the client (by "pre-expiring" it):
            Cache-Control: max-age=0.  Not all caches will revalidate the
            document in every case.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>HTTP/1.1 servers must send Expires: old-date (where old-date is a
          date long in the past) on responses containing Set-Cookie response
          headers unless they know for certain (by out of band means) that
          there are no downsteam HTTP/1.0 proxies.  HTTP/1.1 servers may send
          other Cache-Control directives that permit caching by HTTP/1.1
          proxies in addition to the Expires: old-date directive; the
          Cache-Control directive will override the Expires: old-date for
          HTTP/1.1 proxies.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="User Agent Role">
        <section title="Interpreting Set-Cookie">
          <t>The user agent keeps separate track of state information that
          arrives via Set-Cookie response headers from each origin server (as
          distinguished by name or IP address and port).  The user agent
          applies these defaults for optional attributes that are missing:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Version">Defaults to "old cookie" behavior as
            originally specified by Netscape.  See the HISTORICAL section.
            [TODO: Unlikely.]</t>

            <t hangText="Domain">Defaults to the request-host.  (Note that
            there is no dot at the beginning of request-host.)  [TODO: This is
            important to test!]</t>

            <t hangText="Max-Age">The default behavior is to discard the cookie
            when the user agent exits.  [TODO: Interaction with Expires.]</t>

            <t hangText="Expires">The default behavior is to discard the cookie
            when the user agent exits.  [TODO: Interaction with Max-Age.]</t>

            <t hangText="Path">Defaults to the path of the request URL that
            generated the Set-Cookie response, up to, but not including, the
            right-most /.  [TODO: Test!  This seems wrong for paths that are
            just a single slash]</t>

            <t hangText="Secure">If absent, the user agent may send the cookie
            over an insecure channel.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Rejecting Cookies">
          <t>To prevent possible security or privacy violations, a user agent
          must reject a cookie (shall not store its information) if any of the
          following is true:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>The value of the Path attribute is not a prefix of the
            request-URI.  [TODO: This is a lie.]</t>

            <t>The value for the Domain attribute contains no embedded dots or
            does not start with a dot.</t>

            <t>The value for the request-host does not domain-match the Domain
            attribute.  [TODO: Test whether you can set a cookie for a
            subdomain of yourself.]</t>

            <t>The request-host is a FQDN (not IP address) and has the form HD,
            where D is the value of the Domain attribute, and H is a string
            that contains one or more dots.  [TODO: I don't think this is
            right.  foo.bar.baz.com can set a cookie for .baz.com]</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Examples:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>A Set-Cookie from request-host y.x.foo.com for Domain=.foo.com
            would be rejected, because H is y.x and contains a dot.  [TODO: I
            don't think this is right.]</t>

            <t>A Set-Cookie from request-host x.foo.com for Domain=.foo.com
            would be accepted.</t>

            <t>A Set-Cookie with Domain=.com or Domain=.com., will be rejected,
            because there is no embedded dot.</t>

            <t>A Set-Cookie with Domain=foo.com will be rejected because the
            value for Domain does not begin with a dot.  [TODO: This seems
            unlikely, but test!]</t>

            <t>A Set-Cookie with Domain=.co.uk will be rejected because .co.uk
            is a [TODO: public suffix].</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Cookie Management">
          <t>If a user agent receives a Set-Cookie response header whose NAME
          is the same as a pre-existing cookie, and whose Domain and Path
          attribute values exactly (string) match those of a pre-existing
          cookie, the new cookie supersedes the old.  However, if the
          Set-Cookie has a value for Max-Age of zero, the (old and new) cookie
          is discarded.  Otherwise cookies accumulate until they expire
          (resources permitting), at which time they are discarded.  [TODO: Do
          cookies really accumulate like this?  Also, need to talk about
          Expires]</t>

          <t>Because user agents have finite space in which to store cookies,
          they may also discard older cookies to make space for newer ones,
          using, for example, a least-recently-used algorithm, along with
          constraints on the maximum number of cookies that each origin server
          may set.  [TODO: Consider recommending a cookie eviction strategy
          that works in practice.]</t>

          <t>If a Set-Cookie response header includes a Comment attribute, the
          user agent should store that information in a human-readable form
          with the cookie and should display the comment text as part of a
          cookie inspection user interface.  [TODO: I think the Comment
          attribute is a fantasy.]</t>

          <t>User agents should allow the user to control cookie destruction.
          An infrequently-used cookie may function as a "preferences file" for
          network applications, and a user may wish to keep it even if it is
          the least-recently-used cookie.  One possible implementation would be
          an interface that allows the permanent storage of a cookie through a
          checkbox (or, conversely, its immediate destruction).  [TODO:
          Remove?]</t>

          <t>Privacy considerations dictate that the user have considerable
          control over cookie management.  The PRIVACY section contains more
          information.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Sending Cookies to the Origin Server">
          <t>When it sends a request to an origin server, the user agent sends
          a Cookie request header to the origin server if it has cookies that
          are applicable to the request, based on
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>the request-host,</t>

            <t>the request-URI, and</t>

            <t>the cookie's age.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>The syntax for the header is:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork type="abnf2616">
<![CDATA[
   cookie          =       "Cookie:" cookie-version
                           1*((";" | ",") cookie-value)
   cookie-value    =       NAME "=" VALUE [";" path] [";" domain]
   cookie-version  =       "$Version" "=" value
   NAME            =       attr
   VALUE           =       value
   path            =       "$Path" "=" value
   domain          =       "$Domain" "=" value
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>[TODO: This syntax is entirely wrong.]</t>

          <t>The following rules apply to choosing applicable cookie-values
          from among all the cookies the user agent has.
          <list>
            <t>Domain Selection
            <list>
              <t>The origin server's fully-qualified host name must
              domain-match the Domain attribute of the cookie.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Path Selection
            <list>
              <t>The Path attribute of the cookie must match a prefix of the
              request-URI.  [TODO: Need a more complex algorithm here involving
              the / character.]</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>Max-Age Selection
            <list>
              <t>Cookies that have expired should have been discarded and thus
              are not forwarded to an origin server.</t>
            </list>
            </t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>If multiple cookies satisfy the criteria above, they are ordered
          in the Cookie header such that those with more specific Path
          attributes precede those with less specific.  Ordering with respect
          to other attributes (e.g., Domain) is unspecified.  [TODO: Figure out
          the correct ordering.]</t>

          <t>Note: For backward compatibility, the separator in the Cookie
          header is semi-colon (;) everywhere.  A server should also accept
          comma (,) as the separator between cookie-values for future
          compatibility.  [TODO: Test whether servers actually do this.]</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Sending Cookies in Unverifiable Transactions">
          <t>[TODO: This entire section seems like a fantasy.]</t>

          <t>[TODO: Consider explaining how third-party cookie blocking
          works.]</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="How an Origin Server Interprets the Cookie Header">
        <t>[TODO: This section appears to be nonsense.]</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Caching Proxy Role">
        <t>One reason for separating state information from both a URL and
        document content is to facilitate the scaling that caching permits.  To
        support cookies, a caching proxy must obey these rules already in the
        HTTP specification [TODO: If they're already in the HTTP specification,
        aren't they redundant here?]:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Honor requests from the cache, if possible, based on cache
          validity rules.</t>

          <t>Pass along a Cookie request header in any request that the proxy
          must make of another server.</t>

          <t>Return the response to the client.  Include any Set-Cookie
          response header.</t>

          <t>Cache the received response subject to the control of the usual
          headers, such as Expires, Cache-Control: no-cache, and Cache-Control:
          private.</t>

          <t>Cache the Set-Cookie subject to the control of the usual header,
          Cache-Control: no-cache="set-cookie".  (The Set-Cookie header should
          usually not be cached.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Proxies must not introduce Set-Cookie (Cookie) headers of their own
        in proxy responses (requests).</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Examples">
      <section title="Example 1">
        <t>Most detail of request and response headers has been omitted.
        Assume the user agent has no stored cookies.
        <list style="numbers"> 
          <t>User Agent -&gt; Server
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="request"'>
    POST /acme/login HTTP/1.1
    [form data]
              </artwork>
              <postamble>User identifies self via a form.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>Server -&gt; User Agent
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="response"'>
    HTTP/1.1 200 OK
    Set-Cookie: Customer="WILE_E_COYOTE"; Version="1"; Path="/acme"
              </artwork>
              <postamble>Cookie reflects user's identity.  [TODO: This is
              insecure.]</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>User Agent -&gt; Server
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="request"'>
    POST /acme/pickitem HTTP/1.1
    Cookie: $Version="1"; Customer="WILE_E_COYOTE"; $Path="/acme"
    [form data]
              </artwork>
              <postamble>User selects an item for "shopping basket."</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>Server -&gt; User Agent
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="response"'>
    HTTP/1.1 200 OK
    Set-Cookie: Part_Number="Rocket_Launcher_0001"; Version="1"; Path="/acme"
              </artwork>
              <postamble>Shopping basket contains an item.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>User Agent -&gt; Server
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="request"'>
    POST /acme/shipping HTTP/1.1
    Cookie: $Version="1";
            Customer="WILE_E_COYOTE"; $Path="/acme";
            Part_Number="Rocket_Launcher_0001"; $Path="/acme"
    [form data]
              </artwork>
              <postamble>User selects shipping method from form.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>Server -&gt; User Agent
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="response"'>
    HTTP/1.1 200 OK
    Set-Cookie: Shipping="FedEx"; Version="1"; Path="/acme"
              </artwork>
              <postamble>New cookie reflects shipping method.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>User Agent -&gt; Server
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="request"'>
    POST /acme/process HTTP/1.1
    Cookie: $Version="1";
            Customer="WILE_E_COYOTE"; $Path="/acme";
            Part_Number="Rocket_Launcher_0001"; $Path="/acme";
            Shipping="FedEx"; $Path="/acme"
    [form data]
              </artwork>
              <postamble>User chooses to process order.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t>Server -&gt; User Agent
            <figure>
              <artwork type='message/http: msgtype="response"'>
    HTTP/1.1 200 OK
              </artwork>
              <postamble>Transaction is complete.</postamble>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>[TODO: This example is really silly.  We shouldn't be recommending
        this at all.]</t>

        <t>The user agent makes a series of requests on the origin server,
        after each of which it receives a new cookie.  All the cookies have the
        same Path attribute and (default) domain.  Because the request URLs all
        have /acme as a prefix, and that matches the Path attribute, each
        request contains all the cookies received so far.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Example 2">
        <t>This example illustrates the effect of the Path attribute.  All
        detail of request and response headers has been omitted.  Assume the
        user agent has no stored cookies.</t>

        <t>Imagine the user agent has received, in response to earlier
        requests, the response headers
          <figure>
            <artwork type="example">
Set-Cookie: Part_Number="Rocket_Launcher_0001"; Version="1";
        Path="/acme"
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        and
          <figure>
            <artwork type="example">
Set-Cookie: Part_Number="Riding_Rocket_0023"; Version="1";
        Path="/acme/ammo"
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>A subsequent request by the user agent to the (same) server for URLs
        of the form /acme/ammo/...  would include the following request header:
          <figure>
            <artwork type="example">
Cookie: $Version="1";
        Part_Number="Riding_Rocket_0023"; $Path="/acme/ammo";
        Part_Number="Rocket_Launcher_0001"; $Path="/acme"
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>Note that the NAME=VALUE pair for the cookie with the more specific
        Path attribute, /acme/ammo, comes before the one with the less specific
        Path attribute, /acme.  Further note that the same cookie name appears
        more than once.</t>

        <t>A subsequent request by the user agent to the (same) server for a
        URL of the form /acme/parts/ would include the following request
        header:
          <figure>
            <artwork type="example">
Cookie: $Version="1"; Part_Number="Rocket_Launcher_0001"; $Path="/acme"
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>Here, the second cookie's Path attribute /acme/ammo is not a prefix
        of the request URL, /acme/parts/, so the cookie does not get forwarded
        to the server.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Implementation Considerations">
      <t>Here we speculate on likely or desirable details for an origin server
      that implements state management.</t>

      <section title="Set-Cookie Content">
        <t>An origin server's content should probably be divided into disjoint
        application areas, some of which require the use of state information.
        The application areas can be distinguished by their request URLs.  The
        Set-Cookie header can incorporate information about the application
        areas by setting the Path attribute for each one.</t>

        <t>The session information can obviously be clear or encoded text that
        describes state.  However, if it grows too large, it can become
        unwieldy.  Therefore, an implementor might choose for the session
        information to be a key to a server-side resource.  [TODO: Describe
        briefly how to generate a decent session key.]</t>

        <t>[TODO: We could recommend that servers encrypt and mac their cookie
        data.]</t>

        <t>[TODO: Mention issues that arise from having multiple concurrent
        sessions.]</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Implementation Limits">
        <t>Practical user agent implementations have limits on the number and
        size of cookies that they can store.  In general, user agents' cookie
        support should have no fixed limits.  [TODO: Why not?]  They should
        strive to store as many frequently-used cookies as possible.
        Furthermore, general-use user agents should provide each of the
        following minimum capabilities individually, although not necessarily
        simultaneously:  [TODO: Where do these numbers come from?]
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>at least 300 cookies</t>

          <t>at least 4096 bytes per cookie (as measured by the size of the
          characters that comprise the cookie non-terminal in the syntax
          description of the Set-Cookie header)</t>

          <t>at least 20 cookies per unique host or domain name</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>User agents created for specific purposes or for limited-capacity
        devices should provide at least 20 cookies of 4096 bytes, to ensure
        that the user can interact with a session-based origin server.</t>

        <t>The information in a Set-Cookie response header must be retained in
        its entirety.  If for some reason there is inadequate space to store
        the cookie, it must be discarded, not truncated.</t>

        <t>Applications should use as few and as small cookies as possible, and
        they should cope gracefully with the loss of a cookie.  [TODO: Could
        mention latency issues that arise from having tons of cookies.] </t>

        <section title="Denial of Service Attacks">
          <t>User agents may choose to set an upper bound on the number of
          cookies to be stored from a given host or domain name or on the size
          of the cookie information.  Otherwise, a malicious server could
          attempt to flood a user agent with many cookies, or large cookies, on
          successive responses, which would force out cookies the user agent
          had received from other servers.  However, the minima specified above
          should still be supported.  [TODO: These minima still let an attacker
          exhaust the entire cookie store.  There's not much we can do about it
          though.]</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Privacy">
      <section title="User Agent Control">
        <t>An origin server could create a Set-Cookie header to track the path
        of a user through the server.  Users may object to this behavior as an
        intrusive accumulation of information, even if their identity is not
        evident.  (Identity might become evident if a user subsequently fills
        out a form that contains identifying information.)  This state
        management specification therefore requires that a user agent give the
        user control over such a possible intrusion, although the interface
        through which the user is given this control is left unspecified.
        However, the control mechanisms provided shall at least allow the user
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>to completely disable the sending and saving of cookies,</t>

          <t>to determine whether a stateful session is in progress, and</t>

          <t>to control the saving of a cookie on the basis of the cookie's
          Domain attribute.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Such control could be provided by, for example, mechanisms
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>to notify the user when the user agent is about to send a cookie
          to the origin server, offering the option not to begin a session,</t>

          <t>to display a visual indication that a stateful session is in
          progress,</t>

          <t>to let the user decide which cookies, if any, should be saved when
          the user concludes a window or user agent session, or</t>

          <t>to let the user examine the contents of a cookie at any time.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>A user agent usually begins execution with no remembered state
        information.  It should be possible to configure a user agent never to
        send Cookie headers, in which case it can never sustain state with an
        origin server.  (The user agent would then behave like one that is
        unaware of how to handle Set-Cookie response headers.)</t>

        <t>When the user agent terminates execution, it should let the user
        discard all state information.  Alternatively, the user agent may ask
        the user whether state information should be retained.  If the user
        chooses to retain state information, it would be restored the next time
        the user agent runs.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Protocol Design">
        <t>The restrictions on the value of the Domain attribute are meant to
        reduce the ways that cookies can "leak" to the "wrong" site.  The
        intent is to restrict cookies to one, or a closely related set of
        hosts.  Therefore a request-host is limited as to what values it can
        set for Domain.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <section title="Clear Text">
        <t>The information in the Set-Cookie and Cookie headers is
        transmitted in the clear.  Three consequences are:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Any sensitive information that is conveyed in in the headers is
          exposed to an easedropper.</t>

          <t>A malicious intermediary could alter the headers as they travel
          in either direction, with unpredictable results.</t>

          <t>A malicious client could alter the Cookie header before
          transmission, with unpredictable results.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>These facts imply that information of a personal and/or financial
        nature should be sent over a secure channel.  For less sensitive
        information, or when the content of the header is a database key, an
        origin server should be vigilant to prevent a bad Cookie value from
        causing failures.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Cookie Spoofing">
        <t>[TODO: Mention integrity issue where a sibling domain can inject
        cookies.]</t>

        <t>[TODO: Mention integrity issue where a HTTP can inject cookies
        into HTTPS.]</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Unexpected Cookie Sharing">
        <t>A user agent should make every attempt to prevent the sharing of
        session information between hosts that are in different domains.
        Embedded or inlined objects may cause particularly severe privacy
        problems if they can be used to share cookies between disparate
        hosts.  For example, a malicious server could embed cookie
        information for host a.com in a URI for host b.com.  User agent
        implementors are strongly encouraged to prevent this sort of
        exchange whenever possible.  [TODO: How are they supposed to do
        this?  This section makes little sense.]</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Other, Similar, Proposals">
      <t>[TODO: Describe relation to the Netscape Cookie Spec, RFC 2109,
      RFC 2629, and cookie-v2.]</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document borrows heavily from RFC 2109.  [TODO: Figure out the
      proper way to credit the authors of RFC 2109.]</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Tabled Items">
      <t>Tabled items:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Public suffix.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
